<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Academic</title>
    <link>http://sheenamnarula1993.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Academic</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://sheenamnarula1993.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Cold War</title>
      <link>http://sheenamnarula1993.github.io/post/cold-war/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sheenamnarula1993.github.io/post/cold-war/</guid>
      <description>The cold war was a state of geopolitical tension after second world war between Eastern Bloc(The Soviet Union and its satellite states) and Western Bloc(the United States and its NATO Alies)
Cold war era - 1947 to 1989&amp;frasl;1991. But actually it doesnot have any fix date.
Why is it called cold war : No direct combat or fight between USSR + Allies and US + allies but there were proxy wars like Korean War,Vietnam War and Afghanistan war.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Basic Electronics Part-1</title>
      <link>http://sheenamnarula1993.github.io/post/basic-electronics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sheenamnarula1993.github.io/post/basic-electronics/</guid>
      <description>(NO DEFINITIONS ,ONLY UNDERSTANDING) We all have heard the term, Electricity.
But when we need to explain this term, we can see the working fan, glowing tube and yes, after plugging in phone&amp;rsquo;s charger, simply we can see the increasing percentage sign. Have you ever tried to explore, what is this Electricity ? What does this contain due to which phone&amp;rsquo;s battery is charging and i am able to use it in daily life and yes, what is this term charging means ?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Basic Electronics Part-2</title>
      <link>http://sheenamnarula1993.github.io/post/basic-electronics-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sheenamnarula1993.github.io/post/basic-electronics-part-2/</guid>
      <description>(NO DEFINITIONS ,ONLY UNDERSTANDING) In basic electronics Part-2, I explained about the charge carriers,&amp;ldquo;Electrons&amp;rdquo;.After rubbing, these get knocked off and get stationary. But now the question is how we actually get non-stop flow of electricity that we actually use in daily life.
For this, we need to know some facts about materials.
As every material is made up of atoms but not with the same type of atoms. With some types of materials, such as metals, the outermost electrons in the atoms are so loosely bound that they chaotically move in the space between the atoms of that material by nothing more than the influence of room-temperature heat energy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>India-US Relations</title>
      <link>http://sheenamnarula1993.github.io/post/india-us-relations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sheenamnarula1993.github.io/post/india-us-relations/</guid>
      <description>A hotline is a point-to-point communications link in which a call is automatically directed to the preselected destination without any additional action by the user when the end instrument goes off-hook. An example would be a phone that automatically connects to emergency services on picking up the receiver.
3 military excercises performed with US now a days -
 Vajra Prahar Yudh Abhyas Shatrujeet 2006  But it was not the same in history.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>